Preliminary Inventory to the John Penley Papers TAM.501
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
John Penley Papers
1980-2000
TAM.501
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
Penley, John.
Box 1-2
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John Penley Photographs Collection (Photos 268).
John Penley Photographs Exhibit: http://www.flickr.com/photos/tamiment/sets/72157620867253660/
Historical/Biographical Note
John Penley is a photographer and activist for some thrity yeras and has been associated numerous causes, including AIDs activism, the Squatters' Rights movement in New York City's East Village and Lower East Side, the rights of homeless people, and others. Penley's current photo blog can be found at: http://jpenleypixcom.blogspot.com/
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains magazine and newspaper clippings thatinclude Penley's photographs or are related to his photographic and journalistic interests, leaflets and handbills (including some original artwork) concerning the squatters rights movement. Legal documents from Penley's suit against the New York City Police Department and then Mayor Edward Koch relating to Penley's 1987 arrest (at a rally he organized ot register homeless people to vote), are also included, as are Freedom of Information Act documents and Penley's 1991 New York City Police Department press pass. There is also also a file of legal documents relating to Penley's 1982 arrest and sentencing for trespassing at the Savannah River nuclear power plant in South Carolina, as part of an anti-nuclear movement protest. AIDS activism in particular is extensively documented in a related collection also held by the Library, the unprocessed John Penley Photograph Collection (Photos 268), consisting of eleven boxes containing slides, 35mm negatives, prints in varying sizes, contact sheets, mostly in color, that document Act Up, Housing Works, needle exchange and other harm reduction activity, and that also include coverage of homeless groups, other issues and organizations, and notable historic figures pertaining thereto. Some of Penley's photography was done on a freelance basis for the New York Times. Penley's current photo blog can be found at: http://jpenleypixcom.blogspot.com/
PLEASE DIRECT FURTHER INQUIRIES TO: peter.filardo@nyu.edu
ACT UP New York (Organization).; Penley, John.; AIDS (Disease) |x Political aspects |z New York (State) |z New York.; Antinuclear movement |z United States.; Documentary photography |z New York (State) |z New York.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.).; Photographers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Squatters |z New York (State) |z New York.; Tompkins Square Park Riot, New York, N.Y., 1988.
- Arrest of Penley and His Suit Against the Mayor and the Police in Connection: Legal Documents, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Clippings with Penley Photos or Related to His Life and Work, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Criminal Trespassing, Rivervale Nuclear Plant, South Carolina: Clippings, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Criminal Trespassing, Rivervale Nuclear Plant, South Carolina: Legal Documents, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Freedom of Information Act Requests and Other Related Material, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Leaflets, Handbills, and Posters, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Leaflets, Original Artwork for, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Publications with Penley's Photographs, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Working Press Pass Issued by New York Police Department, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Oversized Newspapers (box 2), 1980s-1990s (Box 2)